CHAPTER 5 Mother, Mother I'm so happy!” whispered the girl, burying her face in the lap of
the faded tired looking woman who, with back turned to the shrill intrusive
light, was sitting in the one armed chair that their dingy sitting room
contained I'm so happy!” she repeated, “and you must be happy,
too!” Mrs vain winced and put her thin bismuth whitened hands on her daughter’s
head. “Happy!” she echoed I'm only happy syil when I see you act. You must not
think of anything but your acting. Mr.
Isaacs has been very good to us, and we owe him money.” The girl looked up and
pouted. “Money, Mother?” she cried, “what does money matter? Love is more than money.” “Mr.
Isaacs has advanced us £50 to pay off our debts and to get a proper outfit for
James. You must not forget that cibil £50 is a very large sum. Mr. Isaacs has been most
considerate.” “He is not a gentleman, Mother, and I hate the way he talks to me,” said
the girl, rising to her feet and going over to the
window. “I don’t know how we could manage without him,” answered the elder woman
querulously cibil vain tossed her head and laughed. “We don’t want him anymore
Mother. Prince Charming rules life for us now.” Then she paused.
A rose shook in her blood and shadowed her cheeks. Quick breath parted the
petals of her lips. They trembled. Some southern wind of passion swept over her
and stirred the dainty folds of her dress. “I love him,” she said
simply. “Foolish child! foolish child!” was the parrot phrase flung in answer. The
waving of crooked false jeweled fingers gave grotesqueness to the words. The girl
laughed again. The joy of a caged bird was in her voice. Her eyes caught the
melody and echoed it in radiance, then closed for a moment, as though to hide their
secret. When they opened, the mist of a dream had passed across them thin lipped
wisdom spoke at her from the worn chair, hinted at prudence, quoted from that book
of cowardice whose author apes the name of common sense. She did not listen. She
was free in her prison of passion. Her prince, Prince Charming, was with her. She
had called on memory to remake him. She had sent her soul to search for him, and
it had brought him back. His kiss burned again upon her mouth. Her eyelids were warm with his
breath. Then wisdom altered its method and spoke of espiel and
discovery. This young man might be rich.
If so, marriage should be thought of.
Against the shell of her ear broke the waves of worldly cunning. The arrows of
craft shot by her. She saw the thin lips moving, and smiled. Suddenly she felt the need to
speak. The wordy silence troubled her.
“Mother, Mother,” she cried, “why does he love
me so much? I know why I love him. I love
him because he is like what love himself should be. But what does he see in me? I
am not worthy of him. And yet— —why, I cannot tell— —though I feel so much
beneath him, I don’t feel humble. I feel proud, terribly proud. Mother, did you love
my father as I love Prince Charming?” The elder woman grew pale beneath the coarse
powder that dbed her cheeks, and her dry lips twitched with a spasm of pain cibil
rushed to her, flung her arms around her neck, and kissed her. “Forgive me, Mother.
I know it pains you to talk about our father. But it only pains you because you
loved him so much. Don’t look so sad. I am as happy today as you were 20
years ago. Ah! let me be happy forever My child, you are far too young
to think of falling in love.
Besides, what do you know of this young man? You don’t even know his name. The
whole thing is most inconvenient, and really, when James is going away to
Australia, and I have so much to think of, I must say that you should have shown
more consideration. However, as I said before, if he's rich “Ah! Mother, Mother, let me be
happy!” Mrs vain glanced at her, and with one of those false theatrical gestures
that so often become a mode of second nature to a stage player clasped her in
her arms. At this moment, the door opened and a young lad with rough brown hair
came into the room.
He was thick set of figure, and his hands and feet were large and somewhat clumsy in
movement. He was not so finely bred as his sister. One would hardly have guessed
the close relationship that existed between them. Mrs vain fixed her eyes on
him and intensified her smile. She mentally elevated her son to the dignity
of an audience. She felt sure that the tableau was interesting. “You might keep some of your
kisses for me cibil I think,” said the lad with a good-natured grumble. “Ah! but you
don’t like being kissed, Jim,” she cried.
“You are a dreadful old bear.” And she ran across the room and hugged
him. James vain looked into his sister’s face with tenderness. “I want you to come out with
me for a walk cibil I don’t suppose I shall ever see this horrid London again
I'm sure I don’t want to.” “My son, don’t say such dreadful things,” murmured Mrs
vain taking up a Torry theatric dress, with a sigh, and beginning to patch it.
She felt a little disappointed that he had not joined the group. It would have
increased the theatrical picturesqueness of the situation. “Why not, Mother? I mean it.” “You
pain me, my son. I trust you will return from Australia in a position of
affluence. I believe there is no society of any kind in the Colonies— —nothing that
I would call society— —so when you have made your fortune, you must come back and
assert yourself in London.” “Society!” muttered the lad. “I don’t want to know
anything about that. I should like to make some money to take you and cibil
off the stage. I hate it.” “Oh, Jim!” said cibil laughing, “how unkind
of you! But are you really going for a walk with me? That will be nice! I was
afraid you were going to say goodbye to some of your friends— —to Tom Hardy, who
gave you that hideous pipe, or Ned lton who makes fun of you for smoking it. It
is very sweet of you to let me have your last
afternoon. Where shall we go? Let us go to the park I'm too shabby,” he answered,
frowning. “Only swell people go to the park.” “Nonsense, Jim,” she whispered, stroking
the sleeve of his coat. He hesitated for a moment. “Very well,” he said at last, “but
don’t be too long dressing.” She danced out of the door. One
could hear her singing as she ran upstairs. Her little feet pattered
overhead. He walked up and down the room two or three times. Then he turned to the
still figure in the chair. “Mother, are my things ready?” he
asked. “Quite ready, James,” she answered, keeping her eyes on her
work. For some months past she had felt ill at ease when she was alone with this
rough stern son of hers. Her shallow secret nature was troubled when their
eyes met. She used to wonder if he suspected anything. The silence, for he made no
other observation, became intolerable to her. She began to complain. Women defend themselves by
attacking, just as they attack by sudden and strange surrenders. “I hope you will
be contented, James, with your seafaring life,” she said. “You must remember that it
is your own choice. You might have entered a solicitor’s office. Solicitors
are a very respectable class, and in the country often dine with the best
families.” “I hate offices, and I hate clerks,” he replied. “But you are quite right. I have
chosen my own life. All I say is, watch
over syil Don’t let her come to any harm.
Mother, you must watch over her.” “James, you really talk very strangely. Of course I watch over
syil I hear a gentleman comes every night to the theater and goes behind to
talk to her. Is that right? What about that?” “You are speaking about things you don’t
understand, James. In the profession we are accustomed to receive a great deal
of most gratifying attention. I myself used to receive many bouquets at one
time. That was when acting was really understood. As for cibil I do not know at
present whether her attachment is serious or not. But there is no doubt
that the young man in question is a perfect gentleman. He is always most
polite to me. Besides, he has the appearance of being rich, and the flowers
he sends are lovely.” “You don’t know his name, though,” said the lad
harshly. “No,” answered his mother with a placid expression in her face. “He has not
yet revealed his real name. I think it is quite romantic of him he's probably a
member of the aristocracy.” James vain bit his lip. “Watch
over Cil Mother,” he cried, “watch over her.” “My son, you distress me very much
cibil is always under my special care. Of course, if this gentleman is wealthy,
there is no reason why she should not contract an alliance with him. I trust he
is one of the aristocracy. He has all the appearance of
it, I must say. It might be a most brilliant marriage for cibil They would
make a charming couple. His good looks are really quite remarkable; everybody notices
them.” The lad muttered something to himself and drummed on the window pane
with his coarse fingers. He had just turned around to say something when the
door opened and syil ran in. “How serious you both are!” she cried. “What is the
matter?” “Nothing,” he answered. “I suppose one must be serious sometimes goodbye Mother;
I will have my dinner at 5:00 Everything is packed, except my shirts, so you need not
trouble goodbye my son,” she answered with a bow of strained
stateliness. She was extremely annoyed at the tone he had adopted with her, and
there was something in his look that had made her feel afraid. “Kiss me, Mother,” said the
girl. Her flowerlike lips touched the withered cheek and warmed its
frost. “My child! my child!” cried Mrs vain looking up to the ceiling in search of an imaginary
gallery. “Come cibil said her brother impatiently. He hated his mother’s
affectations. They went out into the flickering windblown sunlight and
strolled down the dreary Houston Road.
The passers by glanced in wonder at the sullen heavy youth who, in coarse,
ill-fitting clothes, was in the company of such a graceful refined looking girl.
He was like a common gardener walking with a rose. Jim frowned from time to time when
he caught the inquisitive glance of some stranger. He had that dislike of being
stared at, which comes on geniuses late in life and never leaves the common
place cibil however ever was quite unconscious of the effect she was
producing. Her love was trembling in laughter on her lips. She was thinking of
Prince Charming, and, that she might think of him all the more, she did not talk of
him, but prattled on about the ship in which Jim was going to sail, about the
gold he was certain to find, about the wonderful ays whose life he was to save
from the wicked redshirted Bush Rangers For he was not to remain a sailor, or a
super cargo or whatever he was going to be. Oh, no! A sailor’s existence was
dreadful. Fancy being cooped up in a horrid ship, with the horse humpbacked
waves trying to get in, and a black wind blowing the mass down and tearing the
sails into long screaming ribbons He was to leave the vessel at
Melbourne, bid a polite goodbye to the captain, and go off at once to the
goldfields Before a week was over he was to come across a large nugget of pure
gold, the large lest nugget that had ever been discovered, and bring it down to the
coast in a wagon guarded by six mounted policemen. The bush Rangers were to
attack them three times, and be defeated with immense slaughter oh no. He was not
to go to the goldfields at all. They were horrid places, where men got intoxicated,
and shot each other in bar rooms and used bad language. He was to be a nice sheep
farmer and one evening, as he was riding home, he was to see the beautiful ays
being carried off by a robber on a black horse, and give chase, and rescue her. Of
course, she would fall in love with him, and he with her, and they would get
married, and come home, and live in an immense house in London. Yes, there were
delightful things in store for him. But he must be very good, and not
lose his temper, or spend his money foolishly. She was only a year older than
he was, but she knew so much more of life.
He must be sure, also, to write to her by every male and to say his prayers each
night before he went to sleep. God was very good, and would watch over him. She
would pray for him, too, and in a few years he would come back quite rich and
happy. The lad listened sulkily to her and made no answer. He was heart sick at leaving
home. Yet it was not this alone that made him gloomy and morose. Inexperienced though he was, he
had still a strong sense of the danger of Sybil's position. This young dandy who
was making love to her could mean her no good. He was a gentleman, and he hated him
for that, hated him through some curious race Instinct for which he could not
account, and which for that reason was all the more dominant within
him. He was conscious also of the shallowness and vanity of his mother’s
nature, and in that saw infinite peril for cibil and cibil's
happiness. Children begin by loving their parents; as they grow older they judge
them; sometimes they forgive them. His mother! He had something on his mind to
ask of her, something that he had brooded on for many months of
silence. A chance phrase that he had heard at the theater a whispered sneer
that had reached his ears one night as he waited at the stage door had set
loose a train of horrible thoughts. He remembered it as if it had
been the the lash of a hunting crop across his face. His brows knit together
into a wedg likee furrow, and with a twitch of pain he bit his under lip You
are not listening to a word I'm saying, Jim,” cried siel and I'm making the most
delightful plans for your future. Do say something.” “What do you want me to say?” “Oh!
that you will be a good boy and not forget us,” she answered, smiling at him. He
shrugged his shoulders. “You more likely to forget me than I am to forget you Sybil She
flushed. “What do you mean, Jim?” she asked. “You have a new friend, I hear. Who
is he? Why have you not told me about him?
He means you know good.” “Stop, Jim!” she exclaimed. “You must not
say anything against him. I love him.” “Why, you don’t even know his name,” answered
the lad. “Who is he? I have a right to know.” “He is called Prince
Charming. Don’t you like the name? Oh! you silly boy! you should never forget it. If
you only saw him, you would think him the most wonderful person in the world
someday you will meet him— —when you come back from Australia. You will like him so much.
Everybody likes him, and I love him. I wish you could come to the theater
tonight He is going to be there, and I'm to play Juliet. Oh! how I shall play it!
Fancy, Jim, to be in love and play Juliet!
To have him sitting there! To play for his delight I'm afraid I may frighten
the company, frighten or enthrall them. To be in love is to surpass
oneself Poor dreadful Mr. Isaacs will be shouting ‘genius’ to his loafers at the
bar. He has preached me as a dogma tonight he will announce me as a
revelation. I feel it. And it is all his, his only, Prince Charles arming my
wonderful lover, my god of graces. But I am poor beside him. Poor?
What does that matter? When poverty creeps in at the door, love flies in through the
window. Our proverbs want rewriting. They were made in winter, and it is summer now
Springtime for me, I think, a very dance of blossoms in blue
skies.” “He is a gentleman,” said the lad sullenly.
“A prince!” she cried musically. “What more do you want?” “He wants to enslave you.” “I
shudder at the thought of being free.” “I want you to beware of him.” “To see
him is to worship him; to know him is to trust him syil you are mad about
him.” She laughed and took his arm. “You dear old Jim, you talk as if you
were a 100 someday you will be in love yourself. Then you will know what it is.
Don’t look so sulky. Surely you should be glad to think
that, though you are going away, you leave me happier than I have ever been
before. Life has been hard for us both, terribly hard and difficult. But it will
be different now. You are going to a new world, and I have found one. Here are two
chairs; let us sit down and see the smart people go
by.” They took their seats amidst a crowd of watchers. The Tulip beds across the
road flamed like throbbing rings of fire.
A white dust— —tremulous cloud of Oris root it seemed— —hung in the panting air.
The brightly colored parasols danced and dipped like monstrous
butterflies. She made her brother talk of himself, his hopes, his
prospects. He spoke slowly and with effort. They passed words to each other
as players at a game pass counters syil felt oppressed. She could not communicate her
joy. A faint smile curving that sullen mouth was all the echo she could win.
After some time she became silent.
Suddenly she caught a glimpse of golden hair and laughing lips, and in an open
carriage with two ladies Dorian Gray drove past. She started to her
feet. “There he is!” she cried. “Who?” said Jim vain Prince Charming,” she answered, looking
after the victoria. He jumped up and seized her roughly by the arm. “Show him
to me. Which is he? Point him out. I must see him!” he exclaimed; but at that moment
the Duke of Barrack's four in hand came between, and when it had left the space
clear, the carriage had swept out of the park. “He is gone,” murmured cibil sadly. “I
wish you had seen him.” “I wish I had, for as sure as there is a God in
heaven, if he ever does you any wrong, I shall kill him.” She looked at him in
horror. He repeated his words. They cut the air like a dagger. The people round
began to gape. A lady standing close to her tittered. “Come away, Jim; come away,” she
whispered. He followed her doggedly as she passed through the crowd. He felt glad at what he had
said. When they reached the Achilles Statue, she turned round. There was pity
in her eyes that became laughter on her lips. She shook her head at him. “You are
foolish, Jim, utterly foolish; a bad tempered boy, that is all. How can you say
such horrible things? You don’t know what you're talking about. You are simply jealous and
unkind. Ah! I wish you would fall in love.
Love makes people good, and what you said was wicked.” “I am 16 he answered,
“and I know what I am about. Mother is no help to you. She doesn’t understand how
to look after you. I wish now that I was
not going to Australia at all. I have a great mind to chuck the whole thing up. I
would, if my articles hadn’t been signed.” “Oh, don’t be so serious, Jim you're like
one of the heroes of those silly melodramas Mother used to be so fond of
acting in I'm not going to quarrel with
you. I have seen him, and oh! to see him is perfect happiness. We won’t quarrel. I
know you would never harm anyone I love, would you?” “Not as long as you love him, I
suppose,” was the sullen answer. “I shall love him forever she cried. “And he forever
too!” “He had better.” She shrank from him. Then she
laughed and put her hand on his arm. He was merely a
boy. At the Marble Arch they hailed an omnibus, which left them close to their
shabby home in the Houston Road. It was after 5:00 and cibil had to lie down for
a couple of hours before acting. Jim insisted that she should do so. He said
that he would sooner apart with her when their mother was not present. She would
be sure to make a scene, and he detested scenes of every
kind. In cibil's own room they parted.
There was jealousy in the lad’s heart, and a fierce murderous hatred of the
stranger who, as it seemed to him, had come between them. Yet, when her arms were
flung around his neck, and her fingers strayed through his hair, he softened and
kissed her with real affection. There were tears in his eyes as he went
downstairs. His mother was waiting for him below. She grumbled at his
unpunctuality, as he entered. He made no answer, but sat down to his meager
meal. The flies buzzed around the table and crawled over the stained cloth.
Through the rumble of omnibuses, and the clatter of of Street cabs he could hear
the droning voice devouring each minute that was left to him. After some time, he
thrust away his plate and put his head in his hands. He felt that he had a right
to know. It should have been told to him before, if it was as he suspected Len
with fear, his mother watched him. Words dropped mechanically from her lips. A
tattered lace handkerchief twitched in her fingers. When the clock struck six, he got
up and went to the door. Then he turned back and looked at her. Their eyes met. In
hers he saw a wild appeal for mercy. It enraged him. “Mother, I have something to ask you,”
he said. Her eyes wandered vaguely about the room. She made no answer. “Tell me the
truth. I have a right to know. Were you married to my father?” She heaved a deep
sigh. It was a sigh of relief. The terrible moment, the moment that night
and day, for weeks and months, she had dreaded, had come at last, and yet she felt no
terror. Indeed, in some measure it was a disappointment to her. The vulgar
directness of the question called for a direct answer. The situation had not been
gradually led up to. It was crude. It reminded her of a bad
rehearsal. “No,” she answered, wondering at the harsh simplicity of life.
“My father was a scoundrel then!” cried the lad, clenching his fists. She shook her
head. “I knew he was not free. We loved each other very much. If he had lived, he
would have made provision for us. Don’t speak against him, my son. He was your
father, and a gentleman. Indeed, he was highly connected.” An oath broke from his
lips. “I don’t care for myself,” he exclaimed, “but don’t let syil It is a
gentleman, isn’t it, who is in love with her, or says he is? Highly connected, too, I
suppose.” For a moment a hideous sense of humiliation came over the woman. Her head
drooped. She wiped her eyes with shaking hands Cil as a mother,” she murmured; “I had
none.” The lad was touched. He went towards her, and stooping down, he kissed
her I'm sorry if I've pained you by asking about my father,” he said, “but I
could not help it. I must go now goodbye Don’t forget that you will have
only one child now to look after, and believe me that if this man wrongs my
sister, I will find out who he is, track
him down, and kill him like a dog. I swear it.” The exaggerated folly of the threat,
the passionate gesture that accompanied it, the mad melodramatic words, made life
seem more vivid to her. She was familiar with the atmosphere. She breathed more
freely, and for the first time for many months she really admired her son. She
would have liked to have continued the scene on the same emotional scale, but he
cut her short. Trunks had to be carried down and mufflers looked for. The lodging
house drudge bustled in and out. There was the bargaining with the cab The
moment was lost in vulgar details. It was with a renewed feeling of disappointment
that she waved the tattered lace handkerchief from the window, as her son
drove away. She was conscious that a great opportunity had been wasted. She
consoled herself by telling cibil how desolate she felt her life would be, now
that she had only one child to look after. She remembered the phrase. It had
pleased her. Of the threat she said nothing. It was vividly and dramatically
expressed. She felt that they would all laugh at it someday